Finding Aid for Ferdinand Northrup Menefee Papers, 1913-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ferdinand Northrup Menefee Papers 1913-1962
Menefee, Ferdinand Northrup, 1886-
4 linear feet
851816 Aa 2
Professor of engineering mechanics at the University of Michigan. Materials concerning his interest in the St. Lawrence Seaway, his work with the American Concrete Institute's investigation of precast floor systems, and his activities with the American Society of Civil Engineers' Committee on Water Diversion; also subject files on prohibition and immigration policy in the 1920's; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Menefee (donor no. 4670 ) and came to the library in 1968 and 1978.
The collection is open to research.
Ferdinand Northrup Menefee was born on January 7, 1886 in Columbus, Kansas. He received a bachelor of science in civil engineering degree from the University of Nebraska (CE 1932) and finally completed his academic studies at Lawrence Institute of Technology in Detroit (D. Eng.).
Menefee was first hired by Cornell in 1910, but his stay there was brief. Before the year ended he had joined the faculty of the University of Michigan's College of Engineering as an assistant professor. In 1919 he was made a full professor. Menefee continued teaching at Michigan until his death in 1973.
In addition to his responsibilities as an instructor, Menefee was active in professional organizations. He was a life member, and served as President, of the Michigan section of the American Society of Civil Engineers. He was a member and director of the American Concrete Institute. At various times, he chaired the organization's committee on precast floor systems (Committee 711), as well as ACI's membership committee. He was also a member of the Menefee served as president of both organizations.
Menefee was also active in the world of business. He served as a consulting engineer for many firms, was an officer in other forms such as Detroit's Peerless Cement, and helped found still more, such as Lus Trus Plastics, United Engineering Corporation, and the Oak Park Land Co.
In addition to his active academic, professional and business pursuits, Menefee found time for civic affairs. He worked for the pursuits, Menefee found time for civic affairs. He worked for the U.S. Reclamation Service. He was president of the Ann Arbor YMCA and served on that organization's state and national committee. He served as president of the Ann Arbor Board of Public Works and the Ann Arbor Community Fund Association. He also was interested in the Student Christian Association of the University of Michigan.
Menefee belonged to a number of fraternal organizations and clubs. He served as commander of American Legion Post 46, and he belonged to four fraternities. He was elected national president of Sigma Rho Tau.
F.N. Menefee died February 12, 1973.
The Menefee papers documents his professional career as a teacher and as a specialist in engineering mechanics. Following a single folder of Biographical Material, the collection divides into the following series: Correspondence, Speeches, Subject Files, and Photographs.
Subjects:
American Concrete Institute.; American Society of Civil Engineers.; Concrete construction.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Immigrants--United States.; Menefee, Ferdinand Northrup, 1886-; Prohibition--United States.; Saint Lawrence Seaway.; United States--Emigration and immigration.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Engineering Mechanics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Water-supply.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Building materials.; Construction industry--New York (State)--New York.; Machinery.; Menefee, Ferdinand Northrup, 1886-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The quality of the correspondence varies greatly from year to year. While it is not complete on any subject, it is most substantive regarding the construction of the St. Lawrence Seaway Systems and the American Concrete Institute. The correspondence also concerns some of Menefee's many business ventures.
  - 1913-1914, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1923-1962, 38 folders (Box 1)
- Speeches
  Menefee was a frequent speaker. The speech file in the collection is but a random assortment which by chance he happened to save.
  - "Balance and Proportion" (Box 2)
  - Civitan Club 1937 (Box 2)
  - "Citizenship" (Box 2)
  - Community Services, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - "Count Your Many Blessings" (Box 2)
  - "Depression-Bad Break-Blessing" 1933 (Box 2)
  - "English Culture, Human Progress" (Box 2)
  - "The Engineer in Public Life" (Box 2)
  - Freshman Rendezvous (Box 2)
  - Grand Rapids Speech (Box 2)
  - Preparatory Training for Engineers (Box 2)
  - Saline High School 1940 (Box 2)
  - Sigma Rho Tau Speech 1931 (Box 2)
  - "Sitting on the Lid" (Box 2)
  - Sports (Box 2)
  - Vulcans 1930 (Box 2)
  - "Woman's Obligations as Citizens" (Box 2)
  - YMCA (Box 2)
  - YMCA 1929 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Speeches, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Subject File
  The subject file, like the correspondence, deals primarily with the St. Lawrence Seaway and the American Concrete Institute. The seaway material includes a large number of newspaper clippings and supportive material dating back to the 1920's. The ACI material is strongest regarding committee 711, dealing with precast floor systems. The subject file reflects Menefee's opinion on immigration policy in the 1920s, prohibition, and prayer in public schools. It also contains a quantity of material about various water diversion projects.
  - American Concrete Institute
    - 1950 Convention (Box 2)
    - 1951 Convention (Box 2)
    - 1952 Convention (Box 2)
    - 1953 Convention (Box 2)
    - 1953 Board of Directors (Box 2)
    - 1954 Board of Directors (Box 2)
    - 1954 Membership Committee (Box 2)
    - Committee 115 (Box 2)
    - Committee 711, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Advanced Precast System (Box 2)
    - Vacuum Concrete Reports, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 2)
  - Elevated Railways (Box 2)
  - Immigration (Box 2)
  - Prayer in Public Schools 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Presidential Election 1928 (Box 3)
  - Prohibition, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - St. Lawrence Seaway
    - 1922 (Box 3)
    - 1924 (Box 3)
    - 1926-1953, 24 folders (Box 3)
    - 1954-1961, 12 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - The St. Lawrence Seaway by F.N. Menefee (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Printed, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Water Diversion Projects, 8 folders (Box 4)
- Photographs, 3 folders
  - Photograph of Menefee examining blueprints; photographs 1939 illustrating applications of precast concrete floor systems in a New York city slum clearance project; and photographs showing machinery used in stress tests on automobile wheel and axle components. (Box 4)